<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html source_file="/Users/chholbrow/MOOCs/edX_maker/LaTeX2edX/toyx.tex" display_name="Week 5 W/TR Pre-class Reading Summary">



 <!--Heading-->

<p><b>Week 5 Reading Assignment:</b></p>
<p>From the book <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/12">5.4</a>, <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/25">5.6</a>, <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/29">5.8-5.9</a></p>

<h2>
<center> Week 5 W/TR Pre-class Reading Summary </center>
</h2>
<p>
The following is a summary of the reading from the textbook to give you an idea of what is expected to know before coming to class. It does not replace reading the textbook.
</p>
<br/>

<!--Heading Ends Here--> 

<h2>
  <p><center><b><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/12">Capacitors store energy</a></b></center></p>
  <p><center><b><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/12">(Linked to textbook Chapter 5.4)</a></b></center></p> 

</h2>
 
 <h2> Dielectrics and dielectric constant </h2>
  <p>
Dielectric materials are insulators. Unlike metals they do not have free charges to move 
and conduct electricity when an electric field is applied. Instead of free charges, 
dielectrics have (or form) electric dipoles that do not move around much, but which are 
able to rotate and line up with an applied electric field. It is by these dipoles that 
dielectrics and electric fields interact. 
</p>
  <p>
There are solids that have built-in dipole moments and permanent electric fields. By 
analogy to magnets, these substances are called electrets. Quartz is a naturally occurring
 electret. Many electrets are manufactured from synthetic polymers. Teflon is an example. 
 </p>
  <p>
Most dielelctric materials are not electrets; they do not contain intrinsic dipole 
moments. However, applying an electric field to a dielectric will cause dipoles to form 
in it. We say that the electric field &#x201C;polarizes" the dielectric. An electric field
 exerts forces on a dielectric by interacting with its dipoles whether they are intrinsic 
 or induced. 
 </p>
  <p>
Dipoles in a dielectric have their own electric fields, and when aligned by an external 
field, these have a non-zero component in the direction opposite to that of the external 
field; they reduce field intensity in the space near them. This property of dielectrics is
 used to increase the capacitance of capacitors. 
 </p>
  <p>
For many substances in electric fields that are not too large, the amount of dipole moment
 per unit volume is proportional to the applied electric field 
 [mathjaxinline]\vec{E}[/mathjaxinline]. We call the amount of dipole moment in a unit 
 volume the polarization [mathjaxinline]\vec{P}[/mathjaxinline] of the sample and write <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/17">(Reference: textbook equation Chapter 5 p17 equation (5.4.9))</a>
 </p>
  <p>[mathjax]\vec{P}=\varepsilon _0 \chi _{\rm e} \vec{E}[/mathjax]</p>
  <p>
 DBL shows you that a polarization [mathjaxinline]\vec{P}[/mathjaxinline] of a slab 
 results in a surface charge density [mathjaxinline]\sigma _ p = P[/mathjaxinline] and an 
 accompanying electric field of [mathjaxinline]-\vec{P}/\varepsilon _0[/mathjaxinline]. 
 The result is that the effective electric field in the dielectric is reduced by this 
 factor [mathjaxinline]\kappa _{\rm e} = 1+\chi _{\rm e}[/mathjaxinline] and the 
 capacitance increases by a factor [mathjaxinline]\kappa _{\rm e}[/mathjaxinline]. For a 
 parallel plate capacitor this result means <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/5/20">(Reference: textbook equation Chapter 5 p20 equation (5.4.19))</a>
 </p>
  <p>[mathjax]C = \kappa _{\rm e} \varepsilon _0 \frac{A}{d}[/mathjax]</p>
  <p>
 where [mathjaxinline]A[/mathjaxinline] is the area of a plate and 
 [mathjaxinline]d[/mathjaxinline] is the distance between the plates. 
 </p>
</html>
