<?xml version="1.0"?>
<html source_file="/Users/chholbrow/MOOCs/edX_maker/LaTeX2edX/toyx.tex" display_name="Introduction">

 <!--Heading-->

<p><b>Week 6 Reading Assignment:</b></p>
<p>From the book <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/2">6.1-6.3</a>, <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/8/3">8.1-8.3</a>, <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/8/16">8.5</a></p>

<h2>
<center> Week 6 M/T Pre-class Reading Summary </center>
</h2>
<p>
The following is a summary of the reading from the textbook to give you an idea of what is expected to know before coming to class. It does not replace reading the textbook.
</p>
<br/>

<!--Heading Ends Here--> 
  

<h2>
  <p><center><b><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/5">Ohm's Law [mathjaxinline]V=IR[/mathjaxinline]</a></b></center></p>
  <p><center><b><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/5">(Linked to textbook Chapter 6.2)</a></b></center></p> 

</h2>

  <h2> </h2>
  <p>
In some substances, e.g. metals, charges move relatively freely. Because a wire of such a 
substance, e.g., copper, conducts charge from one place to another, we call these substances
 &#x201C;conductors." </p>
  <p>
In most conductors under normal circumstances the movement of the charge is impeded. 
There is, we say, "resistance" to the movement. </p>

  <p><h4>Electric current - amperes: [mathjaxinline]I[/mathjaxinline]</h4> The first ideas
   of moving charge were about charge moving in a tube of conducting material, i.e., a wire.
   Physicists described this behavior by analogy to the flow of water through a pipe, so
   they viewed conduction as a stream of charge, an &#x201C;electric current," moving in
   a wire. Electric current is the rate at which charge passes along the wire. To make
   the idea clear we imagine a surface intersecting the wire and say the electric current
   [mathjaxinline]I[/mathjaxinline] in the wire is the amount of charge 
   [mathjaxinline]\Delta Q[/mathjaxinline] that passes through that surface per time 
   interval [mathjaxinline]\Delta t[/mathjaxinline] <a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/2">(Reference: textbook equation Chapter 6 p2 equation (6.1.1))</a>: 
  </p>
  <p>[mathjax]I = \frac{\Delta Q}{\Delta t} \mbox{ or by the usual limiting process }
       I = \frac{dQ}{dt}.[/mathjax]</p>
  <p>
In the SI electric current is measured in coulomb/second (C/s), and this combination of units
 is called an ampere, abbreviated A. </p>

  <p><h4>Circuits</h4> Electric current will not flow along a wire unless there is a place
   for it to go. For steady currents, the kind we are talking about here, there has to be 
   a source and a sink of charge. A battery is both. Electric current was defined to be the
    flow of positive charge, so current is always said to flow from the + terminal of a 
    battery or power supply to the - terminal. We know now that in metals it is the 
    negatively charged electrons that move from the - terminal to the + terminal, but we 
    continue to use the convention: current flows from + to -. </p>
  
  <p>
Current flows in a loop from + to -. The loop or collection of loops - they can be 
complicated - is called a circuit. Sometimes only part of the loop is drawn. For example, 
the + terminal may be far from the - terminal so the diagram does not look like a loop. Or 
sometimes the sink is drawn as the symbol for &#x201C;ground". But there is always a 
circuit, i.e. some sort of closed loop, around which the current flows. No circuit; no current. 
</p>

 <p>
Because charge is conserved, the sum of currents coming into a junction of wires must equal
 the sum of currents going out. This is called Kirchhoff's current law. 
 </p>
 
  <p><h4>Potential difference: [mathjaxinline]V[/mathjaxinline]</h4> 
  Under most circumstances electric current does not flow unless something pushes it. 
  There has to be an electric field. This field is created by applying a potential difference 
  to the circuit. That is what a battery or power supply does; it applies a potential 
  difference between the + and - terminals. Usually we denote this potential difference by 
  [mathjaxinline]V[/mathjaxinline]. 
  </p>

  <p>
(There is a remarkable exception to this behavior. At sufficiently cold temperatures 
materials called superconductors lose all resistance - it really becomes zero - and once 
begun, current will flow indefinitely around a closed loop without the application of a 
voltage.) 
  </p>
<p><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/5">(Reference: textbook equation Chapter 6 p5 equation (6.2.3))</a></p>


  <p><h4>Resistance: [mathjaxinline]R[/mathjaxinline]</h4> An electric field is needed to 
  make an electric current. The alert reader will ask: Won't an electric field accelerate 
  charges to ever greater speeds? It will unless there is some impediment to the movement 
  of the charges. DBL shows you a microscopic model of how the interaction of moving 
  charges with atoms of the conductor offsets acceleration by the applied electric field
   with the result that on average the electric field produces steady motion rather than 
   accelerated motion of the charges in an electric current. 
   </p>
  <p>
The Bavarian physicist Georg Ohm showed that for many conductors the current 
[mathjaxinline]I[/mathjaxinline] is proportional to the applied voltage 
[mathjaxinline]V[/mathjaxinline]. We call the constant of proportionality the 
&#x201C;resistance" of the wire and denote it as [mathjaxinline]R[/mathjaxinline]. The 
relationship is purely empirical but extremely useful. It is called &#x201C;Ohm's Law" and
 is written: </p>
  <p>[mathjax]V = I R [/mathjax]</p>
  <p>
From the equation you can see that the SI units of 
[mathjaxinline]R[/mathjaxinline] are volts/ampere. This group of units is called an 
&#x201C;ohm" and is abbreviated by [mathjaxinline]\Omega[/mathjaxinline] the capital Greek 
letter omega. 
  </p>
  <p>
Electrical resistance is present in most materials. For example, it is distributed along a 
wire - the longer the wire the more resistance. But for many purposes it is useful to have 
localized lumps of well-defined resistance. These are called &#x201C;resistors" and they 
are manufactured and widely used in electronics. Americans represent resistors by the symbol
&#160;&#160; 
<img src="/static/images/Ameristor.png" width="60"/>.</p>

<p><a href="/course/pdfbook/0/chapter/6/6">(Reference: textbook equation Chapter 6 p6 equation (6.2.6))</a></p>

</html>
